Finding Aid for Media Resources Center (University of Michigan) films and videotapes, 1930s and 1948-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Series I
  - Twelve Caesars of Suetonius, Theodore Buttrey, UM Classics, lectures on the twelve Caesars and Suetonius and his history, Starring reads from Suetonius.
    - Galba, Otho, Vitellus 1980, 851831-I-54-7; Galba, enemy of Nero, a stern, parsimonious, ruthless commander, lost support of the army, was murdered by Otho who ruled for 95 days before being brought down by Vitellus. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Robert Starring, actor
      - Original:, 2-inch video #303
    - Vespasian 1980, 851831-I-54-8; Of the Flavius family, Vespasian is portrayed as a rebuilder, a trustworthy commander, honest and competent. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Robert Starring, actor
      - Original:, 2-inch video #304
    - Titus 1980, 851831-I-54-9; Trained by his father Vespasian to be a "good, upright, decent Roman", Titus ruled for two years, was deified after his death. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Robert Starring, actor
      - Original:, 2-inch video #305
    - Domitian 1980, 851831-I-54-10; Buttrey recapitulates Suetonius' theme that "power corrupts," reviews the period of the civil wars, 44 B.C to 96 A.D. and the 150 years of peace beginning in the reign of Vespasian. Features: Theodore Buttrey, UM-Class.; Robert Starring, actor
      - Original:, 2-inch video #306
  - UM-150, Nine part series on history of the University of Michigan made as part of the sesquicentennial observance based on the book "The Making of Michigan" by Howard Peckham.
    - The Old Frontier 1967, 851831-I-55-1; This program looks at the first fifty years of the University. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; Russell Bidlack, UM-Lib. Sci.; Frank Woodford
      - Original:, Pos. #1312, 2-inch video #307
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-1.flv
    - Best in the West 1967, 851831-I-55-2; The growth of the University of Michigan from 1860 to 1900, when it became the "biggest" and the "Best in the West", is the focus of this program on the James B. Angell years. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; William Hubbard, UM-Med.
      - Original:, Pos. #1313, 2-inch video #308
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-2.flv
    - Visitor-0 1967, 851831-I-55-3; Michigan's famed All-American football great, Tom Harmon, tells the story of Michigan football through interviews with coaches, players, vintage film and photographs. Features: Tom Harmon; H.O. "Fritz" Crisler, UM-Ath.; Bennie Oosterbaan, UM-Ath.; Ernest Allmendinger
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #309, Pos. #1323, 2-inch video #309
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-3.flv
    - Golden Era 1967, 851831-I-55-4; The "golden era" of student life at Michigan - as at all American colleges - was between 1900 and World War I. The traditions are recreated and relived by UM alumni. Features: Howard Peckham. UM-Hist.; Paul Wagner; H.H. Caswell
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #310, Pos. #1324, 2-inch video #310
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-4.flv
    - Great War 1967, 851831-I-55-5; The UM mobilizes for World War I. Footage of war related activity on campus, Fred Wahr discusses anti-German sentiment on campus. Also discussion of the influenza epidemic and a look at the post-war life of "Joe College." Features: Fred Wahr, UM-German; Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #311, Pos. #1325, 2-inch video #311
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-5.flv
    - The Thirties 1967, 851831-I-55-6; When the regents appointed Alexander Grant Ruthven as the 7th President of UM in 1929, they hoped for a quiet period. Instead the depression hit and changed the Ann Arbor campus. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; Harry Carver, UM-Math; Trudy Huebner; Erich Walter, UM-Engl.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #312, Pos. #1326
    - From World War II to Willow Village 1967, 851831-I-55-7; A look at the World War II years when the Michigan campus was mobilized, and the post-war period when the GI bill sent thousands of veterans back to school. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; Ralph Sawyer, UM
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #313, Pos. #1327, 2-inch video #312
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-7.flv
    - A Second Campus 1967, 851831-I-55-8; After World War II the role of research at UM expanded with the growth of the North Campus. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; Geoffrey Norman, UM-VP; James T. Wilson, UM-IST
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #314, Pos. #1319, 2-inch video #313
      - Use copy:, DVD (Box 14)
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-8.flv
    - Michigan Today 1967, 851831-I-55-9; UM President Harlan Hatcher brings the history of the University up to the present day. Michigan today is portrayed in a photographic sequence which sums up the many faces of the University on its 150th birthday. Features: Howard Peckham, UM-Hist.; Harlan Hatcher, UM-Pres.; Wilbur Pierpont, UM-VP.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #315, Pos. #1329, 2-inch video #314
      - Streaming File:, 851831-I55-9.flv
  - Working Musician, The, Fifteen part series in which working musicians demonstrate technique, discuss their instruments and careers.
    - Abe Torchinsky, Tuba 1977, 851831-I-56-1; In this program Torchinsky discusses role of the tuba in the orchestra and demonstrates his warm-up and playing technique. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Abe Torchinsky
      - Original:, 1-inch video #351
    - Rosemary Russell, Mezzo Soprano 1977, 851831-I-56-2; Russell, discusses her rehearsal routines, the importance of interpreting a text and her career as a performer in oratorios, operas, and recitals. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Rosemary Russell, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #352
    - Louis Smith, Trumpet 1977, 851831-I-56-3; Professional jazz trumpet player and UM music faculty member provides a glimpse into life and work of a jazz musician who has quit one-night stands for teaching music. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Louis Smith, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #353
    - Arno Mariotti, Oboe 1977, 851831-I-56-4; What it is like to play the oboe professionally is discussed and demonstrated. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Arno Mariotti, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #354
    - John McCollum, Tenor-Nancy Hodge, Accompanist 1977, 851831-I-56-5; The art of singing and the art of accompanying are discussed. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; John McCollum, Um-Music; Nancy Hodge, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #355
    - Judith Becker, Musicologist 1977, 851831-I-56-6; A description and demonstration of musicology in action with a performance by a UM Javanese gamelan orchestra. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Judith Becker, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #356
    - Gyorgy Sandor, Piano 1977, 851831-I-56-7; A famed Hungarian artist takes us behind the scenes in the art and technique of piano playing. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Gyorgy Sandor, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #357
    - Angel Reyes, Violin 1977, 851831-I-56-8; Informal insights into the lonely life of the soloist from a UM faculty member and renowned violin soloist as he prepares for a performance of a work by Bach. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Angel Reyes, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #358
    - Charles Owen, Percussion 1977, 851831-I-56-9; A demonstration of the art and technique of marimbas, drums, tambourines, gongs, triangles, and vibraphones. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Charles Owen, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #359
    - Jerome Jellinek, Cello; Joseph Gurt, Piano 1977, 851831-I-56-10; How a professional piano duo goes about getting a new piece ready for the concert halls. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Jerome Jellinek, UM-Music; Joseph Gurt, EMU-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #360
    - David Shifrin, Clarinet 1977, 851831-I-56-11; A former principal clarinetist of a major symphony orchestra gives a music lesson in classical clarinet. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music, David Schifrin, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #361
    - Marilyn Mason, Organ 1977, 851831-I-56-12; UM pipe organist leads a tour of her unique music studio, UM's 4,000 seat Hill Auditorium, and explains and demonstrates the pipe organ. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Marilyn Mason, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #362
    - Louis Stout, Horn 1977, 851831-I-56-13; The life and musical times of a prominent American French horn player. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Louis Stout, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #363
    - Elizabeth Bergaman, Dancer 1977, 851831-I-56-14; A look at the life and art of a with choreographer / dancer, with demonstrations of classical, jazz, and modern dance styles. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Elizabeth Bergaman, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #364
    - Donald Sinta, Saxophone 1977, 851831-I-56-15; A demonstration of the versatility of the saxophone with blues, classical flute sound, and even a Japanese Kabuki sound on the saxophone. Features: Jerry Bilik, UM-Music; Donald Sinta, UM-Music
      - Original:, 1-inch video #365
  - Worlds of Abraham Kaplan, Eleven part series, Kaplan gives his personal views on philosophical and social questions.
    - Unreason 1971, 851831-I-57-1; In this program Kaplan provides a blistering attack on the advocates of unreason - the worshipers of feeling, action, and self. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #316, Pos. #3474, 2-inch video #315
    - Love 1971, 851831-I-57-2; Kaplan destroys the myths of love and describes its actualities. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #317, Pos. #3433, 2-inch video #316
    - Morals 1971, 851831-I-57-3; The sexual revolution is examined. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #318, Pos. #3395, 2-inch video #317
    - Loneliness 1971, 851831-I-57-4; Why we are lonely today and what we can do about it is explained. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #319, Pos. #3368, 2-inch video #318
    - Mental Health 1971, 851831-I-57-5; Kaplan discusses the importance of expressing feelings, of being the person who you are, and of accepting yourself, which are the basis of mental health. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #320, Pos. #3468, 2-inch video #319
    - Religion 1971, 851831-I-57-6; Kaplan views organized religion with rational and believing eyes. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #321, Pos. #3437, 2-inch video #320
    - Women 1971, 851831-I-57-7; Kaplan gives his witty, profound, and provocative views on modern women. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #322, Pos. #3438, 2-inch video #321
    - Technology 1971, 851831-I-57-8; A pro-technology discussion by a philosopher who believes that "man is the measure." Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #323, Pos. #3462, 2-inch video #322
    - Free Speech 1971, 851831-I-57-9; In discussing free speech, Professor Kaplan explains what it is, what it isn't, and why it must always be fought for. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #324, Pos. #3463, 2-inch video #323
    - Aging 1971, 851831-I-57-10; Kaplan examines the tragedy of the aged in our youth oriented society. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #325, Pos. #3441, 2-inch video #324
    - Death 1971, 851831-I-57-11; The sanctity of life is linked with the acceptance of death. Professor Kaplan expresses his views on death. Features: Abraham Kaplan, UM-Phil.
      - Original:, 16mm kinescope film, neg. #326, Pos. #3461, 2-inch video #325
  - Singer's Art, The, Thirteen part series takes the viewer inside the world of the concert and opera singer features UM music student and faculty.
    - To Music 1969, 851831-I-59-1; Program 1 looks at the problems of interpretation of music and words. Bassett's composition "To Music" is featured. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Harold Haugh, UM-Music; Leslie Bassett, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #649
    - We Seem to Be One 1969, 851831-I-59-2; The demands of the recital on the singer and pianist are demonstrated in performances of selected songs form "Die Shone Mullerin" by Schubert. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #650
    - La Bonne Chanson 1969, 851831-I-59-3; Art songs written by the contemporary American composers Samuel Barber and John Gruen are examined. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #652
    - The Human Instrument 1969, 851831-I-59-5; The voice in the small instrumental ensemble, solo voice, wind instruments and piano. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #653
    - Making Music Together 1969, 851831-I-59-6; The skills and artistic qualities required in a concert presentation of the solo ensemble are examined. The Michigan Chamber Soloist perform. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Willis Patterson, UM-Music; Oscar Henry, EMU-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #654
    - A Blend of Voices 1969, 851831-I-59-7; The challenges of the singer in the small choir. Works by Bach and R. Schuman are performed by the Michigan Chamber Choir. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Thomas Hilbish, UM-Music; Michigan Chamber Choir
      - Original:, 2-inch video #656
    - Praise and Song 1969, 851831-I-59-8; The University of Michigan Men's Glee Club sings classical contemporary and collegiate songs. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Willis Patterson, UM-Music; Men's Glee Club
      - Original:, 2-inch video #657
    - Ye People, Listen 1969, 851831-I-59-9; An examination of the solo contata of the late Baroque period featuring performances by UM faulty artists. Features: Leslie Guin, Rosemary Russel, N. Hauenstein, G. Rosseels, Charles Fisher, Lawrence Hurst
      - Original:, 2-inch video #658
    - With All Thy Heart 1969, 851831-I-59-10; The oratoria - sacred music for chorus, soloist and orchestra - is examined. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Harold Haugh, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #659
    - So Full of Shapes Is Fancy 1969, 851831-I-59-11; Some instruction of the how's of acting and singing featuring opera instructors from the UM Music School. Features: Theo Alcantara, Katherine Hilgengerg, Eva Likova, Robert Luscomb, all UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #660
    - An Illusion of reality 1969, 851831-I-59-12; An examination of the recitative song (sung dialogue) in opera featuring selections from Verdi's "La Traviata," Gluck's "Orfeo," and Mozart's "Marriage of Figaro." Features: John McMollum, UM-Music; Eva Likova, UM-Music; Ralph Herbert, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #661
    - The Impresario 1969, 851831-I-59-13; A performance of Mozart's humorous light opera "The Impresario" featuring the UM Opera Orchestra and student singers. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Theo Alcantara, UM-Music; Eva Likova, UM-Music
      - Original:, 2-inch video #662
    - A Symphony of Sounds 1969, 851831-I-59-14; A look at the life of a community choral organization and the problems of concert management featuring the directors of the University Musical Society and the Michigan Choral Union. Features: John McCollum, UM-Music; Gail Rector, Donald Bryant
      - Original:, 2-inch video #663
List of Abbreviations for University Uits
Anthro. -- Department of Anthropology
Arch. -- School of Architecture
Art -- Department of Art or School of Art
Astro. -- Department of Astronomy
Ath. -- Division of Athletics
Bio. Sci. -- Department of Biological Sciences
BIR -- Bureau of Industrial Research
Botany -- Department of Botany
Bus. -- School of Business Administration
Class. -- Department of Classical Studies
Comp. -- Dept. of Computer Science or Computing Center
Econ. -- Department of Economics
Ed. -- School of Education
Eng. -- College of Engineering
Engl. -- Department of English
Ext. -- University Extension Service
F E Lang -- Department of Far Eastern Languages
Geog. -- Department of Geography
Geol. -- Department of Geology
Geron. -- Institute of Gerontology
Hist. -- Department of History
Hum. Gen. -- Department of Human Genetics
ILIR -- Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations
ISMRRD -- Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities
ISR -- Institute for Social Research
IST -- Institute of Science and Technology
Jour. -- Department of Journalism
Law -- Law School
Lib. Sci. -- School of Library Science
LSA -- College of Literature Science and the Arts
Math -- Department of Mathematics
Med. -- School of Medicine and/or University Hospital
MMRC -- Michigan Media Resources Center
Music -- School of Music
Pharm. -- Department of Pharmacy
Phil. -- Department of Philosophy
Phy. Ed. -- Department of Physical Education
Pol. -- Department of Political Science
Pres. -- UM President
Psych. -- Department of Psychology
PTP -- Professional Theater Program
Russ. -- Department of Russian Studies
SNR -- School of Natural Resources
Soc. -- Department of Sociology
SW -- School of Social Work
Speech -- Department of Speech
SPH -- School of Public Health
TVC -- Television Center
VP -- University Vice President
VPAA -- Vice President for Academic Affairs
Zool. -- Department of Zoology